

Benjamin Truyman

Technology Lead

Phone: (920) 203-5478 Email: ben@truyman.co URL: bentruyman.com

Profile

I'm a programmer with over 10 years of experience fiddling with various web technologies. I enjoy taking calculated risks by pushing the boundaries of what's thought to be possible by working closely with my team and never settling for the status quo. My focus is in developing scalable and maintainable application architectures by invoking industry best practices, design patterns, and creativity. I measure my work not in SLOC but rather quality, simplicity, portability, and maintainability.

Skills

Web Technologies

HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Ecmascript 5, Coffeescript, SASS, LESS, Stylus

Server-side Technologies

Node.js, MongoDB, CouchDB, Redis, MySQL, PHP, Ruby, Java, Python, Bash/ZSH (sorta server-side)

Testing Tools

Jasmine, Mocha, QUnit

Version Control

Git, SVN, StarTeam

Experience

Technology Lead, Critical Mass; Chicago, IL 2011-Present

- Designed a scalable JavaScript module management framework with 100% test coverage that enforced
 an architecture of highly decoupled modules which interfaced with the client's content management
 system. This was accomplished by implementing patterns and technologies such as pub/sub,
 middleware, sandboxing, and require.js. This library was later refactored to remove the require.js
 dependency making it completely library agnostic.
- Created and helped lead the development of a responsive design framework for a Fortune 100 brand to
 be used by 50+ developers. The framework made use of a custom designed grid system, icon font, SVG
 assets, touch/feature detection, and a responsive JavaScript framework to conditionally invoke behavior
 based on device profile.

- Created a custom designed style framework by adapting various open-source projects such as HTML5
 Boilerplate and Normalize.css as well as a custom grid system developed to be extended to allow for
 responsive design should the requirement be needed.
- Led frontend developement of a major Fortune 100 brand's website. Adapted our internal frontend coding conventions and best practices document to provide the client's several dozens of developers with the resource they require to ensure code consistency and quality across several work streams. Also utilized Grunt and JSHint to help validate code consistency based on our document's guidelines.

• Responsible for performance management of four developers by helping guide career direction, biweekly or monthly 1x1 meetings, establishing goals, and annual reviews.

Senior Developer, Critical Mass; Chicago, IL 2009-2011

- Developed a 44-page internal frontend coding conventions and best practices document with the goal of standardizing and ensuring consistent code style and quality based on personal experience and industry standards. Everything from how for loops should be written to email development.
- Developed a social application for Budweiser's "Grab Some Buds" campaign to enable users to schedule Facebook events on Budweiser.com by creating a roster of friends suggested based on relationship and interaction activity. The application leveraged CSS3 and the Facebook JavaScript client library.
- Created a complex product finder tool that utilized AJAX and Canvas to create a high-performance
 application that worked not only on desktops but also popular tablets to find faucets and accessory
 products. The whole tablet part was out-of-scope, but we knew we could do it.
- Worked with the client's IT staff to help design a solution to allow the client's version control system to ensure the greatest amount of code reuse across their web properties.
- Led development for large projects on Moen by participating in estimation sessions, aiding in architectual decisions, and ensuring code quality.

Developer, Critical Mass; Chicago, IL 2008–2011

- Assisted in directing a redesign project for Moen while developing a number of complex product finder
 tools to help customers better discover and eventually convert by purchasing said products. Also
 implemented an analytics abstraction framework that included both Google Analytics and (now) Adobe
 SiteCatalyst to help enable best coding practices while making it trivial for analysts to further add other
 tagging strategies.
- Developed, from scratch, stockmananddakota.com. Created a Google Analytics abstraction to make it easier to add measurement

Phone: (920) 203-5478 Email: ben@truyman.co URL: bentruyman.com

- Performed and documented a broad site audit of a redesigned Pampers.com to ensure the site
 performed well for end-users. The audit included measuring the amount of HTTP requests, RTTs,
 caching headers, and JavaScript profiling results.
- Helped lead estimation and planning of a redesign project by working with the client's technology
 department to produce HTML flats according to the client's specifications as well as internal information
 architects and designers. The flats included numerous accessibility features such as a carousel and
 tabbed navigation that worked without the presence of JavaScript or CSS. The flats also included a
 Google Maps Enterprise implementation to help allow customers easily find their store locations.

• Developed HTML emails for a large grocery conglomerate and reduced email development process down from eight hours to a half hour through a set of text editor macros and automation scripts.

Education

Illinois Institute of Art - Chicago, Chicago, IL

BFA in Web Design and Interactive Media with Honors, October 2008

Referrals

Available upon request.

Phone: (920) 203-5478 Email: ben@truyman.co URL: bentruyman.com